<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ccolombe12.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ccolombe12.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-04-10T03:10:40+00:00</updated><id>https://ccolombe12.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>The academic wepage of Connor Colombe
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Amoeba Problem</title><link href="https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/Test2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Amoeba Problem" /><published>2023-04-09T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/Test2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/Test2/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="problem-statement">Problem Statement</h2>
<p>The problem statement is as follows:</p>

<p>You start off with one amoeba. Every minute, this ameoba can either:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Do nothing</li>
  <li>Die</li>
  <li>Split into two amoebas</li>
  <li>Split into three amoebas</li>
</ul>

<p>Each of these actions has an equal probability of occurring. All further amoebas behave the
exact same way. What is the probability that the amoebas eventually die off?</p>

<p><em>Challenge: Suppose now the amoeba has the ability to split into up to</em> $n$ <em>amoebas. For large</em> $n$<em>, what is probability that the amoebas eventually die off now?</em></p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>]]></content><author><name>Connor Colombe</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First post! Solution to a classic interview Problem]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Test Post</title><link href="https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/testpost/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test Post" /><published>2023-04-09T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/testpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ccolombe12.github.io/blog/2023/testpost/"><![CDATA[<p>Jean shorts raw denim Vice normcore, art party High Life PBR skateboard stumptown vinyl kitsch. Four loko meh 8-bit, tousled banh mi tilde forage Schlitz dreamcatcher twee 3 wolf moon. Chambray asymmetrical paleo salvia, sartorial umami four loko master cleanse drinking vinegar brunch. <a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p>

<h4 id="hipster-list">Hipster list</h4>
<ul>
    <li>brunch</li>
    <li>fixie</li>
    <li>raybans</li>
    <li>messenger bag</li>
</ul>

<p>Hoodie Thundercats retro, tote bag 8-bit Godard craft beer gastropub. Truffaut Tumblr taxidermy, raw denim Kickstarter sartorial dreamcatcher. Quinoa chambray slow-carb salvia readymade, bicycle rights 90’s yr typewriter selfies letterpress cardigan vegan.</p>

<hr />

<p>Pug heirloom High Life vinyl swag, single-origin coffee four dollar toast taxidermy reprehenderit fap distillery master cleanse locavore. Est anim sapiente leggings Brooklyn ea. Thundercats locavore excepteur veniam eiusmod. Raw denim Truffaut Schlitz, migas sapiente Portland VHS twee Bushwick Marfa typewriter retro id keytar.</p>

<blockquote>
    Testing is always good. We should test more
    -Connor
</blockquote>

<p>Fap aliqua qui, scenester pug Echo Park polaroid irony shabby chic ex cardigan church-key Odd Future accusamus. Blog stumptown sartorial squid, gastropub duis aesthetic Truffaut vero. Pinterest tilde twee, odio mumblecore jean shorts <em>lumbersexual</em>.</p>

\[\int_{0}^\infty e^{-x} x^n \; dx = n!\]]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Just testing how blog posts look]]></summary></entry></feed>